Finding Aid for Office of the Vice President and Secretary of the University (University of Michigan) records, 1935-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of the Vice President and Secretary of the University (University of Michigan) records 1935-2007 1987-2004
University of Michigan. Office of the Vice President and Secretary of the University
2013037 Bimu 2
Executive office at the University of Michigan serving as liaison between the Board of Regents and the executive officers of the university. Coordinates and manages policy and governance matters for and facilitates communication between the two bodies. Responsible for coordinating the business affairs of the Board of Regents and maintaining official Board records. Includes records from Secretaries Richard L. Kennedy, Roberta Palmer, Lisa Tedesco, and Sally Churchill.
36.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records group was received through donations from the Board of Regents (donor number 5932) and the Office of the Vice President and Secretary (donor number 8751 ), between January 1998 and January 2013.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The RG records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The RECORD GROUP record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 37
Patient/Client Records -- Box 37
Eecutive Officer Records -- Boxes 1-37
In the "Act for the establishment of an University," [April 20, 1821] section 4 charged the corporation, or trustees, of the university to "appoint by ballot a Treasurer and a Secretary to continue in office during the pleasure of the corporation; ...that the secretary shall keep a fair journal of the meetings and proceedings of the Corporation, in which the yeas and nays on all questions shall be entered, if required, by two of the trustees present; ..." (University of Michigan Records, 1817-1837, p. 12). The role of Secretary of the University and the Regents has remained part of the University's organization since. The Office of Secretary has, however, undergone numerous changes in its scope and organization.
The first organizational change to the office was in 1864, when the position of Steward of the University, which was created in 1855, was combined with the office of the Secretary. The following years saw added responsibilities for the secretary, including purchasing, account books, keeping a register of students entering the university and of graduates, supervising the care of buildings and grounds, and listing appropriations from the Board (Proceedings of the Board of Regents, 1876-1981, p. 605).
By 1923, the Secretary of the University's duties had altered dramatically. The 1923 revisions to the bylaws defined the duties of the Secretary as being primarily financial. The secretary was essentially the business officer of the board, and kept the account books, supervised purchasing, provided financial information to the board, served as the custodian of deeds, the register of trust funds, and was tasked with keeping an inventory of university items. In 1927, the title of the secretary was changed to "Secretary and Business Manager." These remained the primary functions of the Secretary until the bylaws were amended in 1946 and the duties of the position reverted to acting as custodian of the minutes and supporting documents, as well as serving as custodian of the University Seal. At the time, the Secretary also served as Assistant Vice President, and was responsible to fulfill those duties as outlined in the bylaws, as well.
Under Shirley W. Smith, Secretary of the University from 1908-1944, the office took on an even more pronounced business and financial function. His goal was to centralize control of the University's finances in the Secretary's office. This goal was furthered by the major reorganization of the University that took place under President Alexander Ruthven, which included reorganizing the secretary's office into four divisions: accounting, purchasing, cashier, and investments ("History," Secretary (University of Michigan) records, 1845-1953).
After Smith's retirement in 1944, the office was again reorganized, and the secretarial duties became separate from those of the vice president, and Herbert G. Watkins became Secretary. In 1956, Watkins became ill, and Erich Walter, Assistant to the President, took over the duties of the secretary. In 1959, the Regents combined the offices of Secretary and Assistant to the President, and Walter continued in this position until 1966 when he was replaced by Herbert W. Hildebrandt ("History," Secretary (University of Michigan) records, 1845-1953).
In 1970, Richard Kennedy, Director of State and Community Relations, was appointed Secretary of the University and Assistant to the President, replacing Hildebrandt. In 1984, the Office of State and Community Relations was changed to the Office of Government Relations and the duties of Secretary were aligned with the new office. Following Kennedy's retirement in 1994, the office of Secretary was once again reorganized, its functions again becoming a separate office. Upon Kennedy's retirement, Harold R. Johnson served as interim Secretary until his retirement, upon which Ejner Jensen acted as interim Secretary. Roberta Palmer was appointed to serve as the Secretary of the University in April 1995.
The start of Palmer's tenure was challenging. Taking the reins after Kennedy's departure, the university had been through two interim secretaries, an election year that resulted in two new Regents to orientate, and three months into her service, the resignation of President James Duderstadt. Palmer started out her service by setting specific goals to accomplish during her appointment, including a review of the operation of the Office of the Secretary.
In 1998, President Lee Bollinger, in an effort to streamline the university's administrative structure, again reorganized the office of the Secretary. Walter Harrison, then Vice President for University Relations, took on the duties of the secretary, and his title was changed to Vice President for University Relations and Secretary of the University, reversing the previous administrative change that was made upon Kennedy's retirement. Palmer stayed on as a special adviser to President Bollinger.
That same year, Harrison left the University of Michigan to take an appointment at another university. President Bollinger was faced with reorganizing. The position of Secretary of the University was again separated from all other offices, becoming an independent position in the Office of the President. The title of Vice President was also added to reflect the fact that the Secretary holds executive officer rank. In September of that year, Lisa Tedesco was appointed Vice President and Secretary of the University. In 2005, Tedesco stepped down, and the post was filled by Sally Churchill, the current Vice President and Secretary of the University.
While the office has undergone numerous reorganizations, there have also been changes in responsibilities, although some of the responsibilities are still very similar to those outlined in the 1821 organization of the university. The secretary currently acts as a liaison between the Board of Regents and the officers of the university, is the custodian of the minutes and supporting documents of the Board of Regents, and is the custodian of the University Seal. The duties of the Vice President and Secretary of the University can be found in the Regents' Bylaws 2.11.
University Secretaries
1821 Lemuel Shattuck, Secretary
1821-1835 Charles C. Trowbridge, Secretary
1836-1837 G. Mott Williams, Secretary
1837-1839 Charles W. Whipple, Secretary
1839-1845 Anthony Ten Eyck, Secretary
1846-1852 James Valentine Campbell, Secretary
1852 Charles Henry Palmer, Secretary
1852-1853 Oliver Warner Moore, Secretary
1853-1854 Edward Raymond Chase, Secretary
1854-1856 Alexander Winchell, Secretary
1856-1858 John Livingston Tappan, Secretary
1858-1864 Daniel Leonard Wood, Secretary
1864-1869 John Hiram Burleson, Secretary and Steward
1869-1883 Henry DeWitt Bennett, Secretary and Steward
1883-1908 James Henry Wade, Secretary and Steward
1908-1944 Shirley Wheeler Smith, Vice President and Secretary of the University
1944-1958 Herbert G. Watkins, Secretary of the University and Assistant Vice President
1958-1965 Erich Walter, Secretary of the University, Assistant to the President
1965-1970 Herbert W. Hildebrandt, Secretary of the University and Assistant to the President
1970-1994 Richard L. Kennedy, Vice President for Government Relations and Secretary of the University
1994-1995 Harold R. Johnson, Interim Secretary of the University
1995 Ejner Jensen, Interim Secretary of the University
1995-1998 Roberta Palmer, Secretary of the University
1998 Walter L. Harrison, Vice President for University Relations and Secretary of the University
1998-2005 Lisa A. Tedesco, Vice President and Secretary of the University
2005- Sally Churchill, Vice President and Secretary of the University
The Vice President and Secretary of the University records group (36 linear feet) dates from 1935-2007, with the majority of records dating from 1987-2007, and starts with Secretary Richard L. Kennedy. The majority of the records are from secretaries Kennedy and Lisa Tedesco. The collection includes records related to the performance of the various functions of the Secretary and consists of four major series: Functions and Roles of the Secretary, Board of Regents, Secretaries of the University, and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Nichols Arboretum (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Accounting Office.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Business Office.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan--Commencements.; University of Michigan. Buildings and Grounds Dept.; University of Michigan--Finance.; University of Michigan--Lands.; University of Michigan. Plant Dept.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan. Treasurer.; University of Michigan. Secretary.
- Functions and Roles of the Secretary
  The Functions and Roles of the Secretary series (3 linear feet) includes records that document the performance of duties related to the position of Secretary of the University. Arranged by function, the series can be broken down into several categories that reflect various functions of the position, and includes the Honorary Degree Committee files, files about the Office of the Secretary, University Seal files, and Residency Appeals Committee files.
  - Honorary Degree Committee (Box 1)
    - March -- April 1996 (Box 1)
      [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2033 ]
    - Honorary Degree Documents, 8/1981-2/1996 (Box 1)
    - 1996 (Box 1)
    - December 1998 (Box 1)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Honorary Degree Nominees, May 1999 (Box 1)
    - Honorary Degree -- Regent Readers, 1998-2004 (Box 1)
    - November 29, 1999 (Box 1)
    - May 2000 (Box 1)
    - November 29, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Honorary Degree Nominees, April 2001 (Box 1)
    - November 30, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Honorary Degree Letters, 1996-2001 (Box 1)
    - Honorary Degree, 2000-2004 (Box 1)
    - Honorary Degree Committee, November 2002 (Box 1)
    - Honorary Degree Committee, 2002-2003 (Box 2)
    - November 2003, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Honorary Degree Recipients, 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Honorary Degree Committee, 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Fall 2004 Meeting (Box 2)
    - Honorary Degree Recipients, December 2004 (Box 2)
  - Office of the Secretary
    - History -- University Secretary, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
    - Reorganization, 1996-1998 (Box 2)
    - Search Process, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Search Process Materials, 1994 (Box 2)
  - University Seal
    - Early Documents, 1981-1984 (Box 2)
    - Early Seal Permission Letters, 1962-1989 (Box 2)
    - Historical Seal Information, 1894-1997 (Box 2)
    - Kennedy Licensing Letters, 1983-1994 (Box 2)
    - Seals (Box 2)
    - Seal Log, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Seal Log, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Seal Log, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Residency Appeals Committee (Box 3)
    - Residence Status, 1964-1992 (Box 3)
    - 1974-1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988-1991 (Box 3)
    - 1988-1993 (Box 3)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - 1991-2000, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1993-1995 (Box 3)
    - Appeal Letters, 2000-2005, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Board of Regents
  The Board of Regents series (2.5 linear feet) contains records maintained by the secretary that pertain to the Board of Regents. The series is organized into Correspondence, General Files, Presidential Search, and Regents Files, which contain information relating to individual regents.
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Regents Correspondence -- Affirmative Action, 1975-1998 (Box 4)
    - General, 1968-1991 (Box 4)
    - General, 1970-1988 (Box 4)
    - General, 1994-1997, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - General, 1998-2000, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - General, 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Jensen, Ejner, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Jensen, Ejner -- Regents, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Kennedy, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Kennedy, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Kennedy, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Kennedy, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Kennedy, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Office of General Counsel, 1992-1995 (Box 37)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2095 ]
    - Office of General Counsel, 1995-1997 (Box 37)
      [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2097 ]
    - Office of General Counsel -- Elsa Cole, 1996 (Box 37)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2075 ]
    - Palmer, Roberta, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Palmer, Roberta, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Palmer, Roberta, 1997 (Box 5)
  - General Files
    - Broadcast Ownership Questionnaire, 1993-1998 (Box 5)
    - Budget, June 2000-July 2001 (Box 5)
    - Bylaw Revisions, 1995-1997 (Box 5)
    - Chemistry Building Dedication Regents Photos (Box 5)
    - Elected Regents, 1996 (Box 5)
    - New Regent Orientation, 1994-1996 (Box 5)
    - Opinion re: Elected Boards, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Regental Committees, 1995-1997 (Box 5)
    - Regents' Expenses, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Regents Meetings, 1995-1997 (Box 5)
    - Retreat, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Student Representation, 1975-1995 (Box 5)
  - Presidential Search
    - Advisory Committee, 1967-1996 (Box 5)
    - Candidates' Campus Visit, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Chronology, 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - Consultant, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Court Order, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Court Decisions, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Financial Statements, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Interview Questions, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Legal Action, 1992-1996 (Box 6)
    - Media Reports, 1995-1996 (Box 6)
    - Planning, 1995 (Box 6)
    - Preliminary Presidential Agreement, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Presidential Search Committee, 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Regents' Meetings Transcripts, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Regents' Thank Yous to Candidates, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Regents Files
    - Baker, Deane, 1995-1996 (Box 6)
    - Deitch, Laurence B., 1995-1996 (Box 6)
    - Horning, Daniel D., 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - Maynard, Olivia P., 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - McFee, Shirley, 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - McGowan, Rebecca, 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - Newman, Andrea Fischer, 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - Power, Philip H., 1994-1996 (Box 6)
    - Martin, S. Taylor, 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    - Varner, Nellie M., 1996 (Box 6)
- Secretaries of the University
  The Secretaries of the University series (2.5 linear feet) consists of records on the personal service of two University secretaries, Roberta Palmer and Lisa A. Tedesco. The Palmer files include correspondence, which has been indexed by topic, and documents evaluating the Secretary's office functions. The subseries for Lisa Tedesco documents her service on PACWI (President's Advisory Commission on Women's Issues) and CSSAC (Campus Security and Safety Advisory Committee), which coincided with her time as University Secretary.
  - Roberta Palmer
    - Correspondence Index (Box 6)
    - Correspondence Subjects A-F, 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence Subjects G-M, 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence Subjects O-P, 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence Subjects S, 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence Subjects T-Z, 1995-1997 (Box 6)
    - General Correspondence, 1995-1998 (Box 6)
    - Report of the Secretary of the University to the President and Board of Regents, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Lisa Tedesco
    - PACWI (President's Advisory Commission on Women's Issues)
      - 1998-2002, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1999-2001, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 2002-2003, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 7)
      - 2004-2005 (Box 7)
      - 2005-2006 (Box 7)
      - 2006-2007, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - CSSAC (Campus Security and Safety Advisory Committee)
      - Boylan Report, 1997 (Box 7)
      - Campus Safety Handbook, 2001 (Box 7)
      - Committee Roster and Meeting Dates, 1999-2000 (Box 7)
      - "Developing a Partnership Between a University and a Police Department: The UBOSM -- BPD Partnership Project," 1999 (Box 7)
      - Department of Public Safety, 1992-1997 (Box 7)
      - Interim Report, 1999 (Box 7)
      - LGBT Section, 1999 (Box 7)
      - Materials, 1998 (Box 7)
      - Materials, 1998-1999 (Box 7)
      - Materials, 1993-2000 (Box 7)
      - Materials, 1997-2001 (Box 7)
      - Minutes and Agendas, April -- August, 1998 (Box 7)
      - Minutes and Agendas, August -- December, 1998 (Box 7)
      - Minutes and Agendas, January -- March, 1999 (Box 7)
      - Minutes and Agendas, March -- July 1999 (Box 8)
      - Minutes and Agendas, April 1999-May 2000 (Box 8)
      - Minutes and Agendas, September 1999-July 2000 (Box 8)
      - Minutes and Agendas, January -- March, 2001 (Box 8)
      - Minutes and Agendas, March -- May, 2001 (Box 8)
      - Minutes and Agendas, May -- June, 2001 (Box 8)
      - Minutes and Agendas, June 1999-June 2000 (Box 8)
      - Minutes and Agendas, June 2000-June 2001, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Outstanding Items, 1998 (Box 8)
      - Publications, 1997-1999 (Box 8)
      - Report of the Task Force, 1997 (Box 8)
      - Safety Committee Financial Information, 1998 (Box 8)
      - Safety Publications, 1995-1998 (Box 8)
      - Staffing Special Events, 1998 (Box 8)
      - Workplace Violence, 2001 (Box 8)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (28 linear feet) comprises the bulk of the record group. It contains material related to the business and governance of the university and is arranged alphabetically by subject. As a liaison between the Regents and the Officers of the university, these files document the variety of issues that are dealt with by these bodies as part of the governance process. There are a number of topics that are especially notable, which have been arranged in subseries. The subseries for topical files include: Affirmative Action; Athletics, including the NCAA Certification; Branch Campuses; Executive Officers, including meeting minutes; Health System; Life Sciences Institute, documenting its creation; President's Office; Bylaw 14.06, regarding benefits for University employees regardless of sexual orientation; University Finances, including budget and investment information; and General Files. The General Files include all other subjects. Some of the more notable themes in the General Files include FOIA requests, Citizens Queries, General Correspondence, the Open Meetings Act, and the Ann Arbor Summer Festival.
  - Affirmative Action (Box 9)
    - ACE Report, 1996 (Box 9)
    - Affirmative Action Statement, 1994 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1999-2003 (Box 9)
    - News Clips -- Affirmative Action/Diversity/SAT's, 1999, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Policies, Procedures, and Reports, 1975-1992 (Box 9)
    - Readings, 1997-1998 (Box 9)
    - Title IX, 1975-1987 (Box 9)
  - Athletics
    - Athletic Bylaws, 1995 (Box 9)
    - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, 1963-1993 (Box 9)
    - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, 1970-1991 (Box 9)
    - Fisher, Steve, 1996-1997 (Box 9)
    - General, 1974-1985, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - General, 2003 (Box 9)
    - Gerald R. Ford Award, 2003 (Box 9)
    - Goss, Tom, 2000 (Box 9)
    - Governance, 2000-2001 (Box 9)
    - Interim Report, 1999 (Box 9)
    - Knight Commission, 2000-2003 (Box 9)
    - Knight Foundation Report, 1991 (Box 10)
    - Lapchick Project, 2002-2003 (Box 10)
    - Martin, Carlton -- Plea Agreement, 2000-2001 (Box 10)
    - Martin, Ed, 2002-2004 (Box 10)
    - Medical Advisory Committee, 2000 (Box 10)
    - Men's Gymnastics, 1994 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Stadium, 1997-2001 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Stadium, 2004 (Box 10)
    - NCAA, 1990 (Box 10)
    - NCAA Certification
      - Academic Integrity Subcommittee Agendas and Minutes, 2003-2004 (Box 10)
      - Board of Regents: Response Letter to Self-Study, 2004 (Box 10)
      - Confidential Report "The Experience of the Student-Athlete Through the Lenses of Gender, Race, and Sexuality," 2004 (Box 10)
      - Examples of Committee Appointment Letter, 2003 (Box 10)
      - Executive Summary, 2004 (Box 10)
      - "First Cycle U of M NCAA Certification Report," 1995-1996 (Box 10)
      - Internal Evaluation of Self-Study Process -- Compilation of All Responses, 2003-2004 (Box 10)
      - Internal Evaluation of Self-Study Process -- General Themes Emerging from Responses, 2003-2004 (Box 10)
      - List of "Constituents to Review and to Provide Feedback on Michigan's NCAA Certification Self-Study Report," 2004 (Box 10)
      - NCAA Division I Athletics Certification, 2003-2004 (Box 10)
      - Packet to NCAA Committee on Athletics Certification with Revised Gender Equity and Minority Opportunity Plan, 2004 (Box 10)
      - NCAA Peer Review Team Report, 2004 (Box 10)
      - Response Letter to Peer Review Team Report (UM), 2004 (Box 10)
      - Peer Review Visit -- Bridge Program (NCAA), 2003 (Box 10)
      - Peer Review Visit -- Follow-up, 2004 (Box 10)
      - "Second Cycle Division I Athletics Certification Handbook," 2002-2003 (Box 10)
      - "Second Cycle Division I Athletics Certification Self-Study Instrument," 2002-2003 (Box 10)
      - Self-Study Report -- Executive Summary, 2003-2004 (Box 10)
      - Time Capsule, 2004 (Box 10)
      - University of Michigan Self-Study 2003-2004
        - Introduction (Box 10)
        - Governance and Commitment (Box 10)
        - Academic Integrity Report (Box 10)
        - Fiscal Integrity Report (Box 10)
        - Equity, Welfare, Sportsmanship (Box 10)
    - Ohio State University, 1999 (Box 10)
    - One-on-One Sports Litigation, 2000 (Box 10)
    - Recreational Sports Advisory Committee, 2004 (Box 10)
    - Recreational Sports Annual Reports, 1997-2004 (Box 10)
    - Report of Self-Investigation, 1997 (Box 10)
    - Teeter Survey/Premium Seating Questionnaires, 2003 (Box 10)
    - Title IX, 1999-2003 (Box 10)
    - Title IX, 2003 (Box 10)
    - Varsity Club, 2004 (Box 10)
    - University of Michigan NCAA Self-Study Report, 1995-1996 (Box 10)
    - Women, 1994-2000 (Box 10)
    - Women's Hockey, 1997 (Box 10)
  - Branch Campuses
    - UM Dearborn
      - Athletics, 1987-1991 (Box 10)
      - Chancellorship, 1971 (Box 10)
      - Chancellor Search, 1972-1980 (Box 10)
      - Citizens Advisory Committee, 1975-1993 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence and Reports, 1972-1989, 2 folders (Box 10)
        (includes CD)
      - Correspondence and Reports, 1990-1995 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence and Reports, 1999-2003 (Box 10)
      - Fair Lane Drive, 1978 (Box 10)
      - Rules for Conduct, 1972-1986 (Box 10)
    - UM Flint
      - Communications, 1971-1998, 2 folders (Box 12)